<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The oath of allegeance defended by a sermon preached at a synode in the Metropoliticall Church of Yorke; by Thomas Ireland, Bachelour in Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Ireland, Thomas, b. 1577 or 8.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854771</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20215</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20215)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1209:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The oath of allegeance defended by a sermon preached at a synode in the Metropoliticall Church of Yorke; by Thomas Ireland, Bachelour in Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Ireland, Thomas, b. 1577 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes for Edward Aggas, and are to be sold at his shop vpon Snore hill neere Holborne Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached in defence of the oath of allegeance.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20215:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20215:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE OATH OF ALLEGEANCE, Defended by a Sermon preached at a Synode in the Metropoliticall Church of Yorke;</p>
            <p>By THOMAS IRELAND, Bachelour <hi>in Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. KING. 11.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And <hi>Iehoiada</hi> made a couenant betweene the Lord, and the King, and the people, that they ſhould be the Lords people; likewiſe betweene the King and the people.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes</hi> for <hi>Edward Aggas,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vpon Snore hill neere Holborne Conduit. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20215:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20215:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the moſt reuerend Father in God, <hi>Tobie,</hi> Lord Arch-biſhop of Yorke, Primate and Metropolitane of England My moſt honorable good Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas euery one is made, not onely for himſelfe, but for the Common-wealth; which in a Monarchy (ſuch as ours) conſiſteth in the welfare of the KING: the welfare of the KING con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the loyall and louing hearts of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: their loue and loyalty may moſt appeare in taking or approuing of the Oath of Allegeance: I thought it alſo my duty (moſt reuerend in Chriſt, and my very good Lord) being a publicke Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, by a publicke authority commanded, to gather and declare the proofes thereof out of the word of God. The cauſe is publicke both for this, and for all kingdomes, the place where it was vttered was publicke, being a Synode of the Clergie. The fruit may be publick in ſatiſfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the doubtfull, which here may ſee; that this concerneth not ſo much the Popes, as Gods au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority beſtowed vpon our King: our aduerſaries
<pb facs="tcp:20215:3"/>are growne publick in their libels &amp; contradictions; &amp; therfore this without ambition or vainglory may be publiſht to the world. Thus determining to come in publick, the fauors I haue receiued of your Grace, who both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded me to preach on this theame, &amp; then encouraged me to print this my Sermon, makes me the more preſume to dedicate it vnto your graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous patronage &amp; protection: for although the matter doth not anſwere your iudicious expectation (as a mean artificer often mars good ſtuffe with rude ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) but that the truth wil well enough defend it ſelfe with a bad weapon: yet the matter cannot be but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto your moſt religious loyal Care, which with deare and deepe affection (I know) deſires &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauors by doctrine, diſcipline &amp; example, the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Antichriſt, the peace of Sion, the ſafegard and honor of our bleſſed Soueraigne. Whatſoeuer it is, it is the profeſſion of a cleare conſcience; which if I haue not wel expreſt, there are far ſtronger, which vphold the ſtate of this queſtion; &amp; many may ſucceed in this defence. There is no true Chriſtian-ſubiect, but wold aduêture credit &amp; life in ſo great &amp; good a cauſe: And therfore humbly beſeeching your Grace fauorably to cenſure the firſt aduentures of a young ſcholler. I moſt humbly beſeech the God of Grace, to multiply his graces on your head and hart, vnto your honor in this, and happines in a better world. And ſo reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces moſt humble and deuoted Chapleine,</hi>
Thomas Ireland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="oath_of_allegiance">
            <pb facs="tcp:20215:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Iuramentum Fidelitatis authoritate publica nuper <hi>stabilitum, iure diuino licitum eſt.</hi> This oath of alleageance is lawfull by the word of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of here followes the true copy.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> A. B.</hi> doe truely and ſincerely acknowledge, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, testifie, and declare in my conſcience before God and the world, that our Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> is lawfull King of this Realme, and of all other his Maieſties dominions &amp; countries.</p>
            <p>And that the Pope neither of himſelfe, nor by any authority of the Church or Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other, with any other, hath any power or authority to depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe of any of his Maiſties dominions or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, or to authorize any foraigne Prince to inuade or annoy him or his countries: or to diſcharge any of his ſubiects of their obedience and alleagance to his Maieſtie: or to giue licence or leaue to beare armes, raiſe tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties royall perſon, ſtate or gouernement, or to any of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ſubiects, within his Maieſties dominions.</p>
            <p>Alſo I doe ſweare from my heart, that notwithſtanding any decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or ſentence of excommunication or depriuation made or gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or to be made or granted, by the Pope or his ſucceſſors, or by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny authority deriued, or pretended to be deriued from him, or his Sea, against the ſaid King, his heires or ſucceſſors, or any abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid ſubiects from their obedience, I will beare faith and true allegeance to his Maieſtie, his heires and ſucceſſors, and them will defend to the vttermost of my power, againſt all conspiracies, and attempts whatſoeuer, which ſhall be made againſt his or their perſons, their crownes and dignities, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch ſentence, declaration, or otherwiſe: And I will doe my beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor to diſcloſe or make knowne vnto his Maieſtie, his heires and ſucceſſors, all treaſons and traiterous conspiracies, which I ſhal know or heare of to be againſt him, or any of them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20215:4"/>
And I do further ſweare, that I do from my heart abhorre, deteſt, and abiure as impious and hereticall this damnable doctrine and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; that Princes which be excommunicate or depriued by the Pope, may be depoſed or murthered by their ſubiects, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoeuer. And I do beleeue, and am in conſcience reſolued, that neither the Pope, nor any perſon whatſoeuer, hath power to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue me of this Oath, or any part thereof, which I acknowledge by good and lawfull authoritie to be miniſtred vnto me, and do renounce all pardons and diſpenſations to the contrarie.</p>
            <p>And all theſe things I do plainely and ſincerely acknowledge and ſweare, according to theſe expreſſe words by me ſpoken, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plaine and common ſenſe and vnderſtanding of theſe ſame words, without any equiuocation, or mentall euaſion, or ſecret reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation whatſoeuer; and I make this recognition and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, heartily, willingly, and truly vpon the faith of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. <hi>So helpe me God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20215:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLES. 8.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I aduertiſe thee to take heed to the mouth of the King, and the word of the oath of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Writer of theſe words was <hi>Salomon,</hi> the wiſeſt, and moſt peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able gouernour that euer was in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. The time was in his ancient yeares, when after long experience of both good and euill, he ſaw and ſaid, what was befitting euery ſtate and place. The occaſion, it ſeemes, was the flight and reuolt of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and his complices. The coherence is apparant, how from the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of true wiſedome in the firſt verſe, hee deriues this wiſe aduertiſement in the ſecond; which hee proues in the ſixe following: and in the ninth verſe concludes his owne and his equals miſeries; when a ruler whoſe loue and care deſerueth loue, reapes nought but hate and hurt of his owne people. His purpoſe was, he ſuppoſeth himſelfe a lawfull King, as being ordained of God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and admitted of Iſrael; and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requires a reuerend eſtimation of his worth and words, and that vpon their oathes then ſworne to God on his behalfe.</p>
            <p>The text is diuerſly read of diuerſe interpreters: the vulgar Latine which the formoſt Engliſh followes, reads <hi>Ego os Regis obſeruo:</hi> but this is vnlikely; for being a king, he would not obſerue the king. The later Engliſh in the Church Bibles reades abſolutely: Keepe the kings
<pb facs="tcp:20215:5"/>commandement, without mention of the firſt perſon, mentioned in the originall. The lateſt Engliſh inferres it with a verbe, which <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi> expreſſe with a poſſeſſiue: <hi>Praeſtitutum meum, praeſtitutum Regis obſerua:</hi> all ſounding in one ſence, as if he ſhould haue ſaid: Obey not me only as I am a man (for he was the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt man) but as a king: nor onely while I am a king, but my ſucceſſors whoſoeuer ſhall be king after me: nor onely ſo, but as a publicke Preacher (ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> for ſo the booke is entituled.) I would perſwade euery ſubiect of euery kingdome, to take heede vnto, that is, obey their kinges. Men muſt not onely bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> louers of their perſons, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> louers of their places, nor onely ſo, but with <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> louers of their ſucceſſors; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; for children ſhould inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, as the fortune, ſo the friendſhip of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. Vnto this allegeance were that people double bound by the mouth of the king, and by the oath of God: that is, by the authority of both God and king: for his mouth heere may ſignifie <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the fauour of his countenance, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the fruite of his lippes, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſenſe of his writings, which are improperly called the ſayings of his mouth: or if they would not looke on theſe, yet ſhould they looke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which <hi>Pagnin</hi> expounds either a cauſe, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ground of that, or a cuſtome which had bene long, and was often vſed in Iſrael, or as our tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath, the particulars, <hi>i.</hi> the words of the oath of God, <hi>i.</hi> that godly oath whereby they were bound to their Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>This holy Scripture concerneth vs aſmuch as them, we haue a <hi>Salomon</hi> which without compariſon is wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:20215:5"/>peaceable, and ſanctified: his experience as great, hauing reigned as long a while, ouer as great a people as Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: his occaſions vrgent, by reaſon of thoſe Engliſh fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiues, which haue whet their wits, tongues, pens, and ſwords againſt his throne: his loue and care as much, as appeares in his proceedings: his purpoſe but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of our loue, truſt, and loyalty: the meanes an oath, approued of God, and accuſtomed in all countries: and therefore our miſerable vanitie ſhould be worſe, if we deſpiſe him, or his oath of Allegeance. This is the <hi>Theſis</hi> at this time to be determined, wherein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the greatneſſe of the cauſe, and the ſmalneſſe of mine experience, the multitude of aduerſaries, and the generall ſatisfaction hath bene giuen already by the <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Zadockes:</hi> the King and Biſhops of this land, might either diſ-burden or diſ-hearten mine attempt, yet the conſcience of the truth, the liberty of our Church, the peace of our Common-wealth, the ſafegard of our ſoueraigne, the command of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, the ioint profeſſion of Ciuill and Canonicall obedience, it being the firſt &amp; chiefeſt Canon we ſhould maintaine, our Princes right againſt all traytors, and heretickes, would adde ſpirits vnto the moſt vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men or mindes, to ſpeake in that, which for theſe thouſand yeares hath bene the quarrell of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Giue me leaue therefore I beſeech you, being a yong Diuine to deale in ſtatutes &amp; ſtate-affaires, as farre as I can proue them conſonant vnto Scripture, to follow thoſe illuſtrious lights of the Goſpell, which haue writ before in this argument, as a candle ſomtime ſerues in abſence of the Sun, and to ſpeake aſwell for our euery-way-worthy king, out of the word, as the Canoniſts and Ieſuites do for their both creature and creator, their
<pb facs="tcp:20215:6"/>Popes holineſſe, beſides the word of God; and then as plainly, briefly, and pithily as I can, I will deliuer the diuine lawfulneſſe of the late ſtatute-oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
            <p>This holy Scripture enioynes an obſeruation, and yeeldes reaſon. In this obſeruation we may conſider, whom and how we ſhould obſerue, in this our duties; and in that, the kingly power is declared. The kingly power (to ground that firſt, which is the ground and ſcope of all the reſt) is ordained of God, as appeares by nature and Scripture. Nature ſhewes an heauen to rule this earth, the Sunne to rule the day, the Moone the night, our ſoules to rule our bodies, and our heads by ſenſe and motion, to rule all the reſt of our members: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Cranes, Bees, &amp; Storkes acknowledge their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors in their order &amp; obedience. There is nothing ſo neceſſary, profitable, and beautifull in the ſight of God, Angels, and honeſt men, in our ſelues, in an houſe, in the world or heauen, as this good order is. It is neceſſary, for with it euery ſtate is quiet, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it euery thing is confounded: it is profitable by the peace, honor, and ſafety, which it brings to them which rule, and them which can obey: it is beautiful, for beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is but a proportion and agreement of one part with another. Thus it is excellent in our ſelues, for as in our bodyes, our members are directed by the ſences, ſenſe by reaſon, and reaſon by the Lord; ſo in the politicke bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of our common wealth, the meaner ſort muſt bee ruled by the magiſtrate; the magiſtrate muſt be ruled &amp; ordained of the Prince, as the Prince is of God. It is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in an houſe, when man and wife, children and ſeruants, know their places, and performe their duties: for then thy ſeruants are like ſubiects, thy children like
<pb facs="tcp:20215:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>nobles, thy wife a priuy counſailour, and thy ſelfe as king to determine all controuerſies. It is likewiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in the world, where the baſer creature ſerues the better, the better ſerueth man, and all indifferently ſerue one God. It is more excellent in heauen, whereas the Sunne rules amongſt the reſt of the planets, which are direct, ſtationall, and retrograde; as he comes nearer, or goes further from them: as the planets rule amongſt the reſt of the ſtarres, as hauing ſtronger influence, fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer lights, more ſpheares and motions. As the ſtarres by ſignification of times, and diſpoſition of weather rule all Elements vnder heauen: ſo may we ſay, the king is ouer the Iudges both Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall; the Iudges ouer inferiour officers; and thoſe officers are to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Commons in good order. Yet is it more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in the heauen of heauens, wherein there are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, Arch-angels, and ſeuerall ſorts of immaculate and immortall ſpirits, euery one in their kinde beholding the face, and doing the will of God our common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heauen, like ſo many Courtiers and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable attendants about a Prince. But it is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in God himſelfe, in whom there is no difference of nature, yet a diſtinction of order; there is no diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of parts, yet a relation of number; there is no ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of perſons, yet the firſt is as one fountaine, from which the ſecond &amp; third proceed to ſhew, that though the nature of mankinde be like and equall in many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gifts, yet there may be many reſpects, why ſome be before others, and one before all the reſt. If then we will rule our ſelues, or be rulers in our owne families; if we would enioy the creatures of this world, as we hope to bee like Angels, or to renew the likeneſſe of God himſelfe in vs: wee muſt imitate theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.
<pb facs="tcp:20215:7"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that which is diuine, better and more ancient, is alſo more honorable: now the Monarchie was the firſt policie, for when our firſt parent had begotten many children, hee became a king: his experience was their arbiter, his bleſſing their honour, his curſe their croſſe and heauie puniſhment: as long as he liued, which was very neare the floud, it was vnnaturall for his off-ſpring to ſtriue with him for any preëminence. Thus <hi>Noah</hi> was vnto the ſecond world, and his children in their ſeueral trauailes' to their ſeuerall poſterities, till the rulers au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority grew tyranny, and the peoples libertie tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into licenciouſneſſe, till the crafty mighty got the weaker and ruder to their ſeruice, and all thinges were confuſed, as among <hi>Pharoes</hi> Kine, the worſe eate vp the better without care and conſcience, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the fiſh, the leſſe were deuoured of the greater without any reſpect of humanity. How deteſtable was the ſinne before the floud, when they were care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe eating and drinking, euery one did what they liſt, and tooke them wiues where they luſted? How mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable was the confuſion in the building of Babel, when euery one commanded, but none followed? How abhominable was it when there was no ruler in Iſrael, but euery one did that which was good in his owne eyes, euen ſuch (and ſo much worſe, as our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is weaker in theſe later dayes) would be the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of mankinde, were there not ſome could rule, whom others would obey. Thus the want of kingly power ſhewed it good: and a good the more generall it is, it is the better, whereas many taking parts, it growes particular, &amp; ſo weakens as a riuer cut in many ſtreames. <hi>Quot capita, tot ſenſus,</hi> many heads haue many thoughts,
<pb facs="tcp:20215:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and many faults, and therefore <hi>Homer</hi> ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> one bearing rule, the reſt will better meete, and liue and loue as one, otherwiſe as in a body when the ſoule is gone, there are diuers humors, euery one ſtriuing who ſhould ſooneſt be ſeuered, and thereby bring the body to confuſion. Such is a country without one ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, euery one ſeekes his proper good, and leaues the publike either impaired or diſhonored, as a flocke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſheapheard, as a ſhip without a Pilot, as other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures without man, ſo man would grow wilde and vnwieldie without ſuch an ouer-ſeer. For this cauſe the Gentiles called them Gods which gathered and gouerned ciuill ſocieties together. Whereas <hi>Ariſtocracie</hi> ſeemes the deuice of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> which imagined many principles, and <hi>Democracie</hi> to be the proportion of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> which would haue infinite and irregular beginnings; the <hi>Monarch</hi> is diuine, as only repreſenting Gods owne power. As the Moone offers the ſun-beams with pleaſure to mens eies, which hardly can be looked vpon in his owne beauty, ſo the <hi>Monarchy</hi> preſents the wiſedome, power &amp; iuſtice of the higheſt, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cannot be looked vpon in his own glories, for none hath ſeene God and liued. As then the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael when they durſt not heare the Lord, but would haue <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeake to them, tooke this condition alſo, that they ſhould obey <hi>Moſes</hi> as God himſelfe. So ſince men are ſo weake and timerous, they dare not haue Angels, much leſſe the Lord himſelfe immediatly to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern them; yet it is <hi>ea lege,</hi> that they muſt obey the Lords Liuetenant, as if he ſpake himſelfe, for it is not his, but Gods authority by which he rules.</p>
            <p>This the Scripture often teacheth vs, where wiſdome ſaith: by me kings reigne, and tyrants alſo do poſſeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20215:8"/>the world. Good Kings are Gods images, and euil Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are his executioners: <hi>Aſhur</hi> was his rod, <hi>Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſor</hi> his ſeruant, <hi>Cyrus</hi> his annoynted: <hi>Attila</hi> called himſelfe his ſcourge, and <hi>Tamberlan</hi> his wrath. And therefore although God vſes them as a father doth his rod; firſt correct his children by them, and then throw them into the fire prepared for them; yet the ſonnes and Saints of God ſhould ſubmit themſelues vnder his inſtruments of correction, not ſo much like a dogge running at the ſtone that is throwne at him, biting the chaine that holds him. <hi>i.</hi> repining at the tyrant whereby God reſtrains him; but looking higher vnto the chiefeſt cauſe of his trouble, Gods anger, which puniſheth: &amp; then lower, vnto the greateſt motiue of Gods anger, their owne ſinne, which deſerues it. If we thus thinke of euill Princes, what muſt we thinke of good? Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it is Gods onely maieſty which appoints, his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice which directs, his power which enables them in this high calling: God hath giuen diuers gifts vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers men, in ſome wiſedome to rule, in ſome willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be ruled: God in his word hath ſet forth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans office and duty: God hath bleſt it with ſucceſſe in euery ſtate and degree. God in his owne people Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el hath ſet forth an example how men ſhould behaue themſelues in this buſineſſe. It was the Lord which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Moſes, Ioſhua, Dauid</hi> and his poſterity to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Iſrael. It was the Lord which moued the peoples hearts to receiue, honour and obey them: for as euery beame from the Sun, and euery branch from the root; in like ſort euery power doth proceed from God.</p>
            <p>Thus by nature and Scripture, kings haue rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſubiects, and therefore ſubiects by the condition of relatiues muſt be ruled by them. Thus Saint <hi>Peter</hi> bad
<pb facs="tcp:20215:8"/>vs feare God, and honour the king: all therefore that hold of S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould be thus counſelled. Thus God, Chriſt, and Chriſtians haue honored them: God cals them Gods, Chriſt names them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> either in <hi>re,</hi> as hauing done, or in <hi>ſpe,</hi> as being able to do much good vnto their people <hi>Iuſtin</hi> ſaith vnto the gouernours; <hi>Deum adoramus, vobis in alijys rebus laeti ſeruimus,</hi> We wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God alone in ſpirit, but in outward things we glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do you ſeruice, <hi>Policarpus</hi> anſwered the Proconſull: <hi>Docemur poteſtatibus quae ſunt</hi> à <hi>Deo deferre honorem, qui religioni non ſit contrarius:</hi> all ſuch honour as is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to religion, we may, nay, we muſt yeeld our Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours: the Chriſtians of the firſt fiue hundreth yeares did ſome reuerence (as is manifeſt by the cunning im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture of <hi>Iulian</hi>) to their images; and ſince beare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues lowly to the chaire of State. A ſimple officer is heeded if he bring but the kings name, a Iudge becauſe he takes his perſon, a meſſenger becauſe hee beares his armes, to ſhewe, the honour that wee owe vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: <hi>Eſter</hi> trembled at the countenance of <hi>Aſſuerus, Iſrael</hi> heard the iudgement of <hi>Salomon,</hi> as if it were the wiſedome of the Lord, people ſhouted out at <hi>Herods</hi> oration, it was the voyce of God not man; this it may be was exceeding flatterie, yet <hi>perfalſi regulam,</hi> it may ſhew the meane, which is with all awfulneſſe to take heed vnto the lookes or words of our Soueraigne; that by practiſing our duties towards them, we may better learne to do them vnto God himſelfe, their place af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foords more experience, their office more occaſions, their meanes more abilitie to be doing good; God hath giuen ſpeciall gifts vnto thoſe he ſets in gouernement, as <hi>Homer</hi> cals them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> like to God, more excellent vnto thoſe hee doth aduance ouer his choſen, as vnto
<pb facs="tcp:20215:9"/>
               <hi>Saul, Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> he giues his iudgments vnto the king, and his righteouſneſſe vnto the kings ſonne, that he may helpe the wronged vnto right, and defend the poore, a diuine ſentence is in the mouth of the king, and his mouth tranſgreſſeth not in iudgment, and therefore we ſhould rather heede his lawes or words then our priuate humors, or ſelfe-conceited affections: ſince they are placed ouer vs, not for their eaſe, as what more carefull then a crowne, it being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſcience of all ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to rule a man the moſt variable of all creatures, but for the common good, it behoues vs to ſerue them, ſaith S. <hi>Peter,</hi> as we would ſerue the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus in generall haue wee ſeene that obſeruation which is due to kings, let vs now take heede vnto the ground of this <hi>(The words of the Oath of God)</hi> wherein we may conſider the forme it was an oath of God, the matter was the words wherein it was conceiued: for a formall difference it is called the oath of God, becauſe euery oath is not of God. Our Sauiour and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> hath forbid all ſwearing, that is, all ſwearing by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whether heauen or earth, gifts or Altars, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or Ieruſalem, becauſe this kind of ſwearing is againſt God, our ſelues, and the condition of an oath. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, for therein we ſhould attribute his attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, omni-ſcience, almightineſſe, and the iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of periuries to the creatures; which glories God wil giue to none other. Againſt our ſelues, for men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſweare by greater then themſelues, ſo that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we make the creatures which are inferiour, to bee better then mankinde. It is againſt the nature of an oath, for euery formall oath is an inuocation, and an imprecation. An inuocation of witneſſe, and an impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="tcp:20215:9"/>of puniſhment, if it be falſe, which neither can be granted of the creature, nor expected of the ſwearer. Our Sauiour and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> forbade all falſe, vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious, and offenſiue ſwearing in our cuſtomarie communication, theſe bee not oaths of God, nor of good, but of euill. An oath of God is made according to his word, and <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith, it muſt haue three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: truth, iudgement, and righteouſneſſe, it muſt be ſolemne vndertaken with due iudgement, it muſt be certaine, the better to aſſure the hearers of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne truth, it muſt bee righteous to determine right from wrong: and being thus it is commanded in the Law: Thou ſhall feare the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt ſerue him, and ſweare by his name, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyed in <hi>Eſay,</hi> that thoſe of the new Couenant of the Goſpell, ſhould ſweare by the name of GOD, it is promiſt a reward, if they will learne the wayes of my people, to ſweare by my name, they ſhall be built vp in the midſt of my people, thoſe which with reuerence performe this duty, ſhall bee edified in faith, and aduanced in Gods kingdome. An oath is a law of Nations, which GOD neuer aboliſhed, a part of the diuine worſhip, for therein wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him <hi>iudicem, indicem</hi> and <hi>vindicem,</hi> as GOD heares our oaths, hee knowes our hearts, as he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes in his wiſedome, he will diſcouer in his iuſtice, &amp; in his iudgment puniſh our double dealing. Such an oath is a means of helpe in all humane vncertainties, for general doctrines (as the Schoole-men ſay) may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by generall concluſions, but particular occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences muſt haue particular confirmation; ſuch confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation cannot come from any ſenſible creature, which knows not what is truth, nor from any man, for <hi>omnis
<pb facs="tcp:20215:10"/>homo mendax,</hi> euerie man is eaſie to be deceiued, and ſo readie to deceiue: it cannot come from Angels, for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than may transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light: it muſt therefore onely come from God alone, who being cald vpon as a witneſſe, will either certifie the matter, or puniſh the forſwearer: let vs therefore take with vs the conditions of <hi>Ieremie.</hi> We may well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take an oath; God often ſwore vnto the Patriarkes, the Patriarkes often ſwore, as appeareth in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſweareth in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> an oath was often vſed of the faithfull, as in equall couenants betweene <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Abimeleck,</hi> in legall vowes as the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> in iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall pleadings, as in the caſe of borrowed goods beeing endamaged: this was vſed of brethren in their bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as betweene <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau;</hi> of captaines in their confederacies, as of <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Nicanor;</hi> of ſeruants to their maiſters, as <hi>Moſes</hi> made an oath to <hi>Iethro</hi> to ſtay with him: Thus Princes often ſwore vnto their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, as the Princes of the congregation did vnto the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> that they ſhould liue; <hi>Salomon</hi> ſwore to <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah,</hi> that he ſhould not be ſlaine for his rebellion: every king when hee takes his Crowne, vndertakes an oath, why ſhould not ſubiects alſo ſweare vnto their Prince? Such was this oath here mentioned of <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it agrees neither to the former clauſe, where he bids vs obſerue the king, nor to the later, where he forbids all reſiſting him; the words are not particularly recited, but the ſenſe is plaine, it required obedience, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad reſiſtance; thus princes oft exacted an oath of their inferiours for performance of their duties: as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did of <hi>Achan,</hi> that hee ſhould confeſſe his faulte: <hi>Ezra</hi> ſwore the Prieſts and Leuites and all Iſraell to do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his word: <hi>Caiphas</hi> adiured Chriſt, hee ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:20215:10"/>confeſſe, whether hee were the Sonne of God, or no: our Kingly Prophet and preacher tooke an oath of <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei,</hi> that he ſhould not take a iourney beyond <hi>Iorden,</hi> and (it may be well) commanded all his people vpon their oaths to keepe their faith to him, againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie <hi>Ieroboam;</hi> thus magiſtrates may well demaund, and ſubiects render oaths.</p>
            <p>Now whether this of Allegeance be ſuch an one or no, ſhall be manifeſt in diſcuſſing it. This oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is in ſome parts affirmatiue, in ſome negatiue: the affirmatiue is either aſſertorie for the preſent, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſorie for the time to come. The firſt propoſition is aſſertory, profeſſing that our ſoueraigne IAMES, is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full king; and promiſſorie bee thoſe parts wherein the ſwearer tenders faith, defence, and the diſcloſing all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies. The negatiue parts concernes the Pope or the ſwearer; in the Pope he denies the ſuperintendence of his authorities, and the violence of his excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: in himſelfe he renounces the benefite of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and the purpoſe of equiuocation.</p>
            <p>This we may call the mouth of the king, becauſe our bleſſed Soueraigne endited it, and yet the oath of God as it proceeded from his wiſedome, and is conſonant with his moſt holy word, which will appeare in proofe of the particulars. If the Pope, the Cardinall, his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lein, or the foule-mouthd exile, would haue named any thing that had bene vnallowable, they might haue ſaued vs a labour; but ſince they do not, becauſe they cannot, we muſt maintaine it all in euery part.</p>
            <p>For the firſt aſſertory propoſition of our Soueraignes lawfull right, I could neuer haue imagined, that it would euer haue bene queſtioned, but that <hi>vir dolorum Doleman</hi> would haue aduanced their titles, <hi>Clemens Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20215:11"/>with his briefes would haue bard euery proteſtant, <hi>tametſi ſanguinis propinquitate niteretur: Tortus</hi> (I ſhame to ſpeake it) counts him for no Catholique, and ſo no Chriſtian, and ſo not of the Church, much leſſe ouer it in iuriſdiction: But our moſt gracious King, hath ſo ſoundly conuinced all ſuch imputations, and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his and our faith to bee ſo conformeable to the Scriptures, that the gates of hell, ſhall neuer preuaile o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it: God hath ſo bleſt his rightfull claime with good ſucceſſe, and iuſt applauſe of his owne and other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that the briefes came farre too ſhort, and periſht by their owne deliuerance to the fire, whither other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they would haue deliuered vs: <hi>Doleman</hi> I remit vnto the report of his owne brother, and the ſeculars of his Religion, which better know, as iuſtly hate, and ſet him out for worſe, then this place or preſent is to be made acquainted with. For our Soueraigne without ambition or flatterie, let me ſay thus much: If ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion can make lawfull, This godly branch is lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued from the bleſſed loynes of Engliſh Kings, which for eight hundreth yeares haue ſwayed the Scepter of this Common-wealth. If inſtitution from God can make a king, what greater proofe hereof can be, then his many deliuerances before, his eaſie and happy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage then, and his hopefull iſſue to continue this for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, beſides the ſpeciall gifts which are onely fit for ſuch a maieſty, that are beſtowed on him; in his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the confirmation of our Goſpel; in his experience (which euer ſince his cradle hath already reigned in a more trouble ſome eſtate) the maintenance of our peace is moſt infallibly promiſed: But his learning is moſt admirable in a Prince of ſuch employments: By his meditations on the Pſalmes, his deteſtation of witches,
<pb facs="tcp:20215:11"/>and the kingly bleſſing that he gaue his princely ſonne, wherein he diſcourſeth ſo diuinely for the Scripture, ſo religiouſlly for the Church, ſo prudently for the Common-wealth, ſo carefully for his Court, and ſo iudiciouſly for other exerciſes, we may well know, that he knows how to gouerne a kingdome. Thoſe, although ſome railing <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> would attribute vnto ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; yet his graue, ſound, and ſufficient compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſcandalous factions and opinions of our Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; his euery-where skilfull moderating in our vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity diſputations, his moſt excellent orations often made vnto the Parliament, may ſatisfie the moſt enuious, and teſtifie to the moſt incredulous, the greatneſſe of his worth. Beyond all theſe is the neuer-inough praiſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie, wherein with ſuch plaineneſſe he deliuers his deepe knowledge, with ſuch mildneſſe he meetes with his aduerſaries, and yet with ſuch acuteneſſe and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of reading, he confutes and retorts all their aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or arguments. Eſpecially the premonition which none but a Prince of equal ſpirit &amp; power durſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, wherin he ſo royally defends the common cauſe of Kings, ſo ſeuerely cenſures the cenſurers, ſo plainly doth he declare his right, profeſſe his faith, diſcouer An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, &amp; expound the Reuelation, and with ſuch loue perſwades to Chriſtian courage, &amp; vnitie, that it effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally demonſtrates him a Prince, not only philoſophical, which <hi>Plato</hi> thought a bleſſedneſſe, but prophetical, which the Scripture counts diuine, his quick inſight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the reach of his priuy Councel, as appeares in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering the powder-blow; his iuſtice mingled with mercies, which thoſe that ſought his life, yet liuing, can teſtifie; his deep wiſdome in deuiſing this iuſt oath, well witnes him not only wiſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Etha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Heman, Chalcol, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:20215:12"/>Darda</hi> the cunning and moſt learned of our aduerſaries, but one for his graces and perfections worthy to rule the world, what man or mind therefore can be ſo baſe, wicked, or peruerſe, which either cannot find, or finding will not confeſſe, or confeſſing will not reioyce in this our happines in enioying him?</p>
            <p>What ſubiect ſhould not promiſe and performe all ciuill faith? Our aduerſaries very wrongfully racke this oath to ſpirituall obedience, for albeit in their owne ſayings they can make mountaines of mole-hils by their mentall reſeruations, yet according to Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin, tuxta mentem eius qui miniſtrat, iurandum eſt,</hi> an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration is to bee taken as the Iudge requiring it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds himſelfe; and this is no more then <hi>iure diuine</hi> ſhould be yeelded vnto princes.</p>
            <p>Thus Saint <hi>Paule</hi> admoniſheth <hi>Titus,</hi> he ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh all, they ſhould be ſubiect and obedient vnto powers and principalities; Saint <hi>Peter</hi> willeth vs to be ſubiect vnto all manner of humane ordinance, whether vnto the king as to the ſuperiour, or to the gouernours that are ſent of him: where I cannot but wonder at the corrupt expoſition of the Ieſuites; which would haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be an ordinance from man, as if it were from his deuiſe, notwithſtanding Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſaid, all power proceedes from God; whereas it is indeed an ordinance for man, or Gods ordering man, as hee did his other creatures in their places and duties. Like to this is that, where they ſay that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies, wee muſt not obey the king, vnleſſe hee ſhall excell in vertues, or otherwiſe, when as the ſame Apoſtle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after bids vs to ſubmit with feare, not onely to the courteous, but alſo to the froward; to which <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naus</hi> alſo conſenting, ſaith, ſome Princes are appointed
<pb facs="tcp:20215:12"/>for profit, &amp; ſome for puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, al fit for thoſe ouer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they rule, and to be taken as appointed of the Lord. Thus the martyrs did ſubmit themſelues vnto their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> being in priſon counſelled his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiechians.</hi> Thus the Chriſtian Souldiers did vnto <hi>Iulian.</hi> Thus the Councels did vnto their Emperors, by whoſe helpe and authority they came together, and confirmed their decrees. Thus the Church the more primitiue it was, it was the purer from diſloyalty, not becauſe, (as our aduerſaries haue imagined) it wanted power, for a little faith would haue remoued mountaines, if it had bene expedient for Chriſtianity: becauſe it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted pride, and heerein would imitate her maiſter Chriſt, which might haue had many legions of Angels, yet had rather yeeld vnto the ciuill ſword of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. It is a nouell doctrine therefore ariſen vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ieſuites to ſay, <hi>Reges</hi> are <hi>proprie ſerui,</hi> very ſlaues vnto their ſubiects, contrarying euen common reaſon by confounding the difference of thoſe rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and peruerting the truth of God. It was not thus in <hi>Perſia,</hi> when the ſecond Squire of <hi>Darius</hi> body ſaid, the king ruled all, all thing were done at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, warfare, tillage, tribute, killing, ſparing, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, waſting, all depended on his pleaſure. It was not ſo with <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> to whom the Reubenites, Gadites, and halfe the tribe of Manaſſe ſaid, whoſoeuer ſhall reſiſt thy will, or will not obey whatſoeuer thou comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, let him be done to death. It was not thus at any time in Iſrael, for whether the kings were faithfull or vngodly, the people euer yeelded ciuill faith. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> when he ſhould firſt annoynt a king, he told the manners of a tyrant, that hee would make his people and their children ſlaues, not becauſe a king ſhould be
<pb facs="tcp:20215:13"/>ſo, but becauſe if hee were ſo, we ſhould rather ſuffer then reſiſt; If the Centurion bid the ſouldiers come, they came; or go, they went; do this or that, and they did it: and ſhall our Generall in all cauſes be leſſe honored then a Centurion? The Iewes were bidden pray for the peace of <hi>Babylon,</hi> with the life of <hi>Nabuchadnetzar,</hi> and of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar</hi> his ſonne; and ſhall we ceaſe to pray for kings, &amp; thoſe that are in authoritie, that we way leade a quiet life vnder them? Without all queſtion, we muſt be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in thought, word and worke: Curſ not the King, no not in thy thought, ſpeake not euill of the ruler of thy people, but rather pray for him, as <hi>Daniel</hi> for <hi>Darius,</hi> though he put him in the Lyons denne. By this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence likewiſe muſt we be readie, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good worke: <hi>Obedientia perfecta, ſua imperfecta relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere;</hi> and ſometimes thou muſt leaue thine owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, to do the buſineſſe of thy Soueraigne. Such is the faith we ſhould performe; vnto which wee muſt alſo ioyne defence; this is as manifeſt in Scripture: the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, holieſt, and mightieſt kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had a ſpeciall guard of <hi>Cherethites</hi> and <hi>Pelethites;</hi> which would neuer haue bene granted of Gods owne people, vnto men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods owne heart, vnleſſ the like might haue the like. It was an honor vnto <hi>Iudah,</hi> that notwithſtanding the treacheries of <hi>Sheba,</hi> yet they ſtood faſt vnto their King from <hi>Iorden</hi> to <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> The Worthies of <hi>Dauid</hi> are alſo counted by their threes and their thirties, as they ſtood more or leſſe for him; in like manner they are not vnworthily moſt honored of our Soueraigne, which haue ſtood moſt in his defence: Like to <hi>Dauid</hi> is he worth many thouſands, &amp; therfore if any danger ſhold happen, he ſhould be kept fartheſt from the reach of it. This is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to defend the defender of the Faith: why ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:20215:13"/>not all defend him, who defendeth all? His ſword cuts off theeues and murtherers, that wee may keepe our goods and bodies in ſafetie; his lawes curbe adulterers, that we may keep our wiues and daughters in chaſtitie; his nauies on ſeas, and forces on land, mainetaine our quiet and ſecuritie; in him as in the <hi>Palladium</hi> or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple haire of <hi>Niſus,</hi> conſiſts the ſafeguard of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale.</p>
            <p>As the King of <hi>Syria</hi> ſayd, fight neither againſt ſmall nor great, but onely againſt the King of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> ſo the Pope, which hath perſecuted vs euer ſince <hi>Wickliffe</hi> with fire and ſword, now fights not againſt ſmall nor great, but hath caſt all his quarrell vpon our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and therefore both ſmall and great muſt fight for him.</p>
            <p>Farre be it then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts for to be like the men of <hi>Belial,</hi> who deſpiſed <hi>Saul,</hi> as if he could not ſaue them; but we muſt be like thoſe, whoſe hearts the Lord had touched for to ſtand with and followe him; not like accurſed <hi>Meroz</hi> which would not helpe, which would not helpe the Lord againſt the mightie: but like to <hi>Zabulon</hi> or <hi>Nepthalim,</hi> who ieoparded their liues to death, with <hi>Barak</hi> and <hi>Debora;</hi> not like to <hi>Ioab,</hi> who for his priuate quarrell, would make <hi>Dauid</hi> naked of his friendes; but rather like <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> which expoſing his owne bodie to perill, preſerued the life of his deere Prince. For as a Serpent will defend his head, and a man his heart, becauſe therein lies the life-blood of their bodies: ſo ſhould euerie ſubiect, their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, being (as <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was) the breath of their noſtrils, and the bleſſing of their ſtate: as <hi>Codrus</hi> did for <hi>Athens,</hi> or <hi>Curtius</hi> for the <hi>Romanes;</hi> or, if I may compare, as
<pb facs="tcp:20215:14"/>Chriſt our Sauiour for his truth, ſo ſhould euery man euen with his owne life redeme the life of his king, on whom ſo many liues depend. <hi>Dulce &amp; decorum est pro patria mori,</hi> euen death were pleaſant and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in ſuch a cauſe; let vs then bee valiant for our Prince, our Citties, and the ſeruice of our God, and let the Lord doe that which is good in his owne eyes, ſo ſhould wee promiſe and performe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>And thereon followes the diſcloſing all conſpiracies, which is a part of true defence, for otherwiſe <hi>qui tacet conſentire videtur,</hi> he that conceales ſeemes to conſent: who can hide fire in his boſome and not bee burnt? who can conceale a miſchiefe and bee guiltleſſe? <hi>Qui non vetat peccare, quum poſiit, iubet,</hi> he that forbids not ſuch a ſinne, fauours, if not furthers it, and it is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe that ſinne, but thoſe that fauour ſinne, that ſhall be puniſhed in Gods iudgement. When <hi>Iezabel</hi> ſhall bee caſt into the bedde of paine, her louers alſo ſhall ſuffer great afflictions: if <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Tereſh</hi> then intend euill againſt <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> it is for <hi>Mardochaeus,</hi> an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruitor to diſcloſe it; if the King of <hi>Aram</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in his priuy chamber worke miſchiefe againſt the King of Iſrael, it is for <hi>Elizaeus</hi> to reueale it; if <hi>Abſalon</hi> or <hi>Adoniah</hi> ſtirre vp rebellion againſt <hi>Dauid</hi> or <hi>Salomon,</hi> it is for <hi>Zadock</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſts, and <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, with all ſpeede poſſible to preuent it. It is the tricke of a <hi>Dalilah,</hi> not to diſcloſe a danger, till the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> be vpon vs; but <hi>Michol</hi> will diſcouer it, euen againſt her owne father, while there is time to fly. Beware then of <hi>Iacobs</hi> curſe, who ſaid of his owne children, when they became brethren in euill: Into their ſecret let not my ſoule enter, let not my
<pb facs="tcp:20215:14"/>honour bee ioyned vnto their aſſembly; ſo grieuous was their crime, he thought it a ſinne to know them, and a ſhame to come amongſt them; <hi>Praeferre patriam liberis Regem decet:</hi> It is a Princes glory to preferre his country before his children, much more is it in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men to ſay with <hi>Ariſtotle, Amicus Plato, magis ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men veritas eſt amica;</hi> Our friends or kindred may bee deare, but our king and common-wealth muſt be dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. As a good Pilot then diſcry the tempeſt, and giue warning, diſcouer treaſon before thou be diſcouered, as a partie; for otherwiſe either the bird of the aire, (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) may vtter the voyce, or the ſtones in the ſtreet, ſaith Chriſt, will cry out the truth; or thine owne mouth may condemne thee like <hi>Iudas,</hi> who could not hold from ſaying, maiſter is it I.</p>
            <p>This may perſwade the lay parties, but the Prieſts in their auricular confeſſion; vſurpe greater authority, in this they wil (their wil is all the reaſon they can yeeld) be like to God himſelfe, to ſee, ſuffer, and couerall; but let them know; their power is not alike to permit ſinners for a ſeaſon, and then puniſh them on a ſodaine; their wiſedome is not like to turne, and vſe the worſt vnto the beſt purpoſes; their iuſtice is not like, the longer they ſuffer ſinne, they cannot ſend the ſorer puniſhment at laſt; their prouidence is not alike, the more the Chriſtian ſhall endure to recompence their patience with more pleaſure, and therefore their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in <hi>poenitentiali foro,</hi> in giuing penance muſt not be like; their preſumption is rather like to <hi>Lucifers</hi> when hee ſaid, <hi>Ego ſimilis,</hi> I will bee like the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: and therefore their puniſhment will not be much vnlike: I, but the ſeale of that holy Sacrament ſhould not be cancelled on ſo ſleight an occaſion? Is that
<pb facs="tcp:20215:15"/>a Sacrament, which hath neither inſtrument nor inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution in holy Scripture? Is that a ſeale which hath no ſealing of Gods holy ſpirit? Can that be counted ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which hath bene polluted with ſuch and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny monſtrous abhominations, as ancient and moderne hiſtories are ſtuffed with? Is the ruine of a kingdome but a ſleight occaſion to breake the promiſe of ſuch a Prieſt? Is that religion either conſcionable or charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which giues couert vnto ſuch Traitors? Is not their Chriſtian liberty, nay their Pontificall authority, made heere the cloke of maliciouſneſſe and ranke villany? Were not their profeſſion the myſterie of iniquitie, they would neuer keepe iniquity ſo ſacred in ſecrecy, that it ſhould neuer bee diſcloſed. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to digge through the wall, <hi>Ieremie</hi> to diſcouer the skirts, <hi>Eſay</hi> to walke naked, the Prophets to lift vp their voyces like trumpets, to tell <hi>Iacob</hi> her ſinnes, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> her tranſgreſſions; but now ſilence and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance not onely tollerates, but promotes the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous proiects and practiſes: Chriſt commands vs, what wee heare in the eare, we ſhould preach on the houſe top, to tell our brethren their faults in priuate; if they mend not, wee muſt call witneſſes, if that ſerue not, wee muſt accuſe them before the congregation; and ſhall the ſhameleſſe life and credit of a Traytor be preferred before the word of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, before a Princes life, &amp; the liues of many thouſand that are innocent? A Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition if he find an infection, is to publiſh it, leſt it ſpread abrode. The Leuitical Prieſt was to denounce a Leprous man vncleane, the Poet could marke a perilous perſon with a blacke coale: <hi>Hic niger eſt, hunc tu Romane caueto:</hi> and ſhall the Miniſter of the Lord behold a fire in his neighbours, his maiſters, his owne houſe (for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth
<pb facs="tcp:20215:15"/>is a common houſhold of vs all;) &amp; further it with his concealement, that it may burne the ſorer with a ſodaine flame? The abſurdities hence enſuing moued the Frier to diſcouer the trayterous purpoſe of the noble man of <hi>Normandie:</hi> the <hi>Iacobin</hi> to manifeſt the treaſonable reſolution of <hi>Barierius;</hi> and <hi>Garnet,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that the laws were iuſt, were made againſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that he was guilty in breaking them: and this I hope ſufficient to diſſwade all true Catholickes from the concealing of all conſpiracies.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus laid the affirmatiue part for a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, the negatiue enſues as a corollary: the firſt that is denyed is the Popes vſurped authority, that neither of himſelfe, nor from the Sea of Rome, or other men or meanes, hee can depoſe Kings, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe kingdomes, diſcharge ſubiects, authorize ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, or licence any to beare armes. That hee cannot of himſelfe, is manifeſt: no man can come to ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour but he that is called of God; and God cals none, except his onely ſonne to ſit ſo neare his throne; much leſſe the Pope, of whom it is experimentally noted of wiſe trauellers: that, the worſt Chriſtians are in Italy, the worſt Italians be the Romanes, the worſt of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes be made Prieſts, the worſt Prieſts are made Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, and the worſt Cardinals are choſen to bee Popes. Among the later Popes, <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> was a good Prince, but no good Prelate, as appeares when he ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this to that by excommunicating her late Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> was a good Prelate, but no good Prince, much leſſe good man; for <hi>Bellarmine</hi> told a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Doctor of our nation: <hi>Quantum capio, quantum ſapio, deſcendit ad infernum;</hi> as farre as I can learne, he went to hell. <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth was a good Prince and
<pb facs="tcp:20215:16"/>Prelat but no good man; for it is a poſition receiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Ieſuites: that <hi>Homo non Chriſtianus, poteſt eſse pon tifex Romanus,</hi> or man that is no Chriſtian may be Pope of <hi>Rome; Clemens Octauus</hi> was a good man for a Pope, a good Prince, and a Prelate for his owne hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, though not for ours; but <hi>Paulus Quintus</hi> that now reignes is none of thoſe, as is manifeſt in his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt our King and Church; in ſo much as <hi>Blackwell</hi> which would haue died for the Prelacie, yet is aſhamed of his tyrannies, and ſaith, hee wants a good counſellor.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>non à ſe,</hi> much leſſe <hi>a ſedes,</hi> the ſeate of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no ſuch priuiledge; for though their faith was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ouer all the word, the faith of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was knowne to God, yet it is now falne to <hi>Mahumetiſme;</hi> though the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> decreed: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe that citie ruled then, it ſhould haue ſome prerogatiue, yet the Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the Biſhop of the primate ſea, ſhould not bee called the ruler of the Prieſts. The truth is, <hi>Rome</hi> hath alwayes beene ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; euen while the wals were building, <hi>Romulus</hi> kild his brother, that he might reigne alone; and till this time <hi>antiquum obtinet,</hi> it continues like it ſelfe: ſo truly do they verifie the rule of their graund maiſter <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,</hi> that in the ſame places, as there haue beene, there will be peculiar like affections; <hi>Rome</hi> as in her begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it was the patterne of all morall vertues, ſo in the beginning of Chriſtianitie, ſhe was the prime-example of true patience: there the tyrants dwelt, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Church, and thoſe moſt, which were nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt them; of the <hi>Romane</hi> Biſhops therefore we may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learne to ſuffer then to rule the world; now as the
<pb facs="tcp:20215:16"/>firſt, euen ſo the ſecond <hi>Rome</hi> is degenerate into worſe manners; the firſt Biſhops were perſecuted, then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, then equalled, then aduanced ouer earthly Kings; firſt they would be called Biſhops, then <hi>Primi,</hi> then Primats, then Princes, then Gods deputies, then Gods themſelues. It is not then their power, but their policie, that hath brought them to this paſſe. As before their garriſons and ſouldiers wan them Empire, ſo now their Colledges are their fortreſſes, the Cardinals their Generals, the Friers their ſoldiers, the pennes their weapons; the ſeculars, and Ieſuits, their Agents and inſtruments which ouercome the world. <hi>Quamuis Roma multis aucta victoriis fines imperii protulerit, minus eſt quod bellicus labor ſubdidit, quam quod pax Chriſtiana ſubiecit.</hi> Although they got much by their warfare, yet their Chriſtian cunning peace, hath got more to their dominion, as a Prophet of their owne foretold and taught. <hi>Tu regere Imperio populos Romane memento, Hae tibi erunt artes, paci<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> imponere nomen.</hi> Like the ſnake, Rome hath bene warmed in the boſome of our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt kingdomes, till it ſtung them vnto death; like iuie ſo long it hath embraced, that it hath eaten vp whole Monarchies; like the Crocodile, by weeping and creeping, it hath got into the beſt eſtates; like old Rome it vſeth all Religion onely for a vantage: he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Kings at ods, and then becoms an arbiter: hee brings kingdomes to the ballance, and makes that weightier, where hee doth propend. As the Romane Emperours would bee counted Monarkes of the world, although their Empire in <hi>Scipioes</hi> iudgement was but a point, and vnder <hi>Traian,</hi> when it flouriſht moſt, it was not the thirtieth part; ſo the Popes will be taken for Gouernours of the world, though that there bee but
<pb facs="tcp:20215:17"/>a little cantle of Europe, which will hold of them. Thus you ſee that it is the citties cuſtome, not the Churches right which makes them thus vſurping.</p>
            <p>For there is no other, no, not Saint <hi>Peter</hi> that can yeeld it them: Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (they ſay) was cald a Rocke, therefore on Saint <hi>Peters</hi> chaire muſt the Church bee built: to which we ſay, that as <hi>Simon</hi> was called <hi>Peter, i.</hi> a rocke, ſo <hi>Peter</hi> was called <hi>Simon, i.</hi> obedient, to ſhew, that they ſhould build ſo, that they might ſtill obey: nay being both <hi>Simon</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> he was after called Satan, to ſhew, the ſucceſſion of that name would after proue Satannicall. But <hi>Peter</hi> had the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, which might looſe or binde: the kingdome of heauen (we confeſſe) was opened by S. <hi>Peters</hi> key, the preaching of the word; but the kingdomes of this earth, are yet reſerued in the power of God, promotion comes not either fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eaſt or Weſt, from North or South, but it is God, that ſets vp one, and pulleth downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: But <hi>Peter</hi> was bidden feed the lambes &amp; ſheep: why? feeding is not fleecing chiefeſt of the flocke; <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was bidden kill and eate; ſuch killing was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, not the confuſion, the mortifying, not the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Gentiles, it was not the killing ſword, but pricking word, which wan <hi>Cornelius</hi> and 3000. at one ſermon: I but <hi>Peter</hi> by walking on the ſea, did get a dominion from ſea to ſea, and from the floud vnto the worlds end: no more (ſay we) then Chriſt, that fled thither, and walk there, becauſe he would not bee made a king. But Chriſt came into S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſhip to ſhew that he would come into S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſea; yet as hee came in, he came out againe; as he deſired Chriſt for to depart from him, for he was a ſinfull man; to ſhew that hee would part from them, when as they parted from his truth:
<pb facs="tcp:20215:17"/>yet <hi>Peter</hi> was foretold his death, and bidden follow, to ſhew, that as he followed in ſuffering, he ſhould follow in reigning: but all this was no more, then hee ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> of the cup and baptiſme, they ſhould be baptized with; no more then hee told his other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, when he bad them take vp his croſſe and follow, promiſing: they that left all for him, ſhould ſit vpon twelue ſeates, and iudge the twelue tribes of Iſrael: who notwithſtanding haue no iudgement in this world. If they ſay, S. <hi>Peter</hi> paid for Chriſt, wee may ſay, the fiſh paid it him; if, how Chriſt was firſt ſeene of <hi>Cephas,</hi> then of the twelue, <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> ſaw him before <hi>Cephas;</hi> if, how S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpoke the firſt and moſt vnto the Iewes of Chriſt, we muſt anſwer, it was becauſe he ſpoke laſt and worſt, when he blaſphemed him. Theſe are the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> whereon <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would build the Popes patrimony; but how abſurdly you may ſee, by that vntempered morter with which hee daubes the Church-gouernment; A monarchy (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) is the beſt, and to this we grant the beſt Monarke, euen Chriſt alone; as the father eſtabliſht him, I haue ſet my king vpon mine holy hill of <hi>Zion.</hi> All thinges according to S. <hi>Paul</hi> hapned vnto the Iewes in a figure (ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>) and therefore our high Prieſthood muſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble theirs; to which we muſt anſwer, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> meanes al things that are there mentioned, for otherwiſe al their ceremonies are to become Chriſtian: the Church indeed, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, is a kingdome, but Chriſt is the king, to whom all power is giuen in heauen and earth: a flocke, but Chriſt is that good ſheepheard: a body, but Chriſt is the head; a ſhip, which the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtles could not guide in the tempeſt, vntill our Sauiour came and ſtilled the waues. God forbid I
<pb facs="tcp:20215:18"/>ſhould here condemne all Metropolitans and Diocae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans; for I know there bee certaine Eccleſiaſticall reſerued caſes in which they may determine: but an vniuerſall, infinite, and incontrollable iuriſdiction, ouer men, Angels, diuels and purgatorie ſoules, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but <hi>Luciferian</hi> (vnto which our aduerſarie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares it) and <hi>Anti-chriſtian.</hi> How can the Pope take on him to direct all truth, and ſalue all miſchiefs in this world, vnleſſe he pull Chriſtes office from his hands? Can any man effectually call, and ſend orders of Miniſters, but Chriſt which enables vs vnto this calling? Can any determine all controuerſies, but the Spirit, that leads into all truth? any make one faith, but one Chriſt, in whom wee truſt? Can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gouerne well all the world, but he muſt bee more then a man; for a man can hardly gouerne his owne family; more then an Angel; for Angels are propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned vnto ſeuerall prouinces in <hi>Daniels</hi> prophecie: He muſt bee equall in iuſtice, power and wiſedome to God himſelfe, who takes no more in charge, then the Pope challengeth. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had a care indeed of all Churches, but it was of all that were conuerted then, far fewer then are now to bee directed; it was in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, praying, preaching, trauelling; which the Popes haue little leaſure to meddle with; it was for edifiyng, not deſtruction, as they now intend. Beeing deſtitute of Scripture, they flie to their owne decretals, whereof ſome are ſo plainely forged, ſome full of ſo plaine falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; the reſidue ſo much partiall, that we may ſay with Chriſt, He that ſpeaketh of himſelfe, ſeeketh his owne glory: and, If I beare witneſſe of my ſelfe, my witneſſe is not true. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did referre the choiſe of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the diſciples, the Councell of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb facs="tcp:20215:18"/>him before the reſt, hee cals himſelfe but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a fellow Elder: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him to his face, as being in place and deed ſuch as might, and ſhould bee blamed; <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, all the Apoſtles had the fame fellowſhip of honour and office; vnto which alſo <hi>Hierome</hi> conſenteth. <hi>Pelagius</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, would not be cald vniuerſal; &amp; thus it was til <hi>Phocas</hi> the murderer of his Maiſter made <hi>Boniface</hi> the third Pope of Prieſts: it is not then from Saint <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much leſſe from Chriſt: Chriſt would haue no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence among the bleſſed Apoſtles, nor haue them reigne as Kings of the nations; he bad the Prieſts giue to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> &amp; as good giue them nothing as not obedience; Chriſt was obedient before his birth when he trauelled for the taxe: all his life had many leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of obedience, he paid tribut vnto <hi>Caeſars</hi> cuſtomers, was conue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted before his deputie; confeſt, his power was from aboue, and ouer him. What greater humility could there be, then that the Son of God, ſhould ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto the ſon of man, the Lord of heauen vnto a lumpe of earth, and the King of Kings, vnto the ſubiect of a King? His death was the ſumme of all obedience, he was obedient vnto the death, euen the death of the croſſe, and learnt obedience in that he ſuffered: the more he ſuffered, he was willing to ſuffer more: this hee neither needed nor deſerued, but that with his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility he would humble his followers vnder temporal authority. Now looke vpon the Pope, how faire he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes him far of: Chriſt would not become a deuider betwixt brethren, but the Pope diuides between Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as <hi>Alexander</hi> did the Eaſt &amp; Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> betweene <hi>Portingale</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi> Chriſt would not aſke his right, albeit he were very neere vnto the crowne: the Pope would haue many crownes, albeit he hath no right in
<pb facs="tcp:20215:19"/>them. Chriſt was a king, yet would ſeeme none: the Pope is none, yet would ſeeme higher: like the Romane Dictators, they deteſt the title, yet arrogate greater po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to make their Senate of Cardinals as good as kings. The Pope therefore is not the ſucceſſor of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> but of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which was neuer great, <hi>Prinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pontificiam potestatemcum Caeſarea coniunxiſſet,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ioyned the Prieſthood and Empire in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; not the ſole Vicar of Chriſt but of Satan, which promiſed all kingdoms vnto thoſe that would fall down and worſhip him; not the God of men, as their Gloſſe pretends, but the man of ſinne, who ſets himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all that is called God on earth, <hi>i.</hi> all ciuill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers.</p>
            <p>There hath bene great contention betwixt the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and the ciuill ſtate, and it hath fared with vs, as <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deons</hi> fleece; when it rained on the fleece, it rained not on the ground; when on the ground, not on the fleece; when the Spiritualty was rich, the Temporality was poore; now the laity is rich, the Spiritualty is poore; I would to God as we might meete in faith, we might in loue, and both bee content one with anothers ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement and proſperity: the ciuill ſtate ſhould bee like a father to prouide for vs, while the the ſpirituall as a Tutor doth inſtruct vs; the ciuill as a good husband ſhould care for ſuch things as are abrode, the ſpirituall as a good huſwife, tend that which is within our doores in our conſcience: the ciuill as our head to guide our outward motions, &amp; the ſpiritual as our hearts for to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our affections: Both of them ſhould be like <hi>Atri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the two Sheepheards of the people, like <hi>Amarias</hi> and <hi>Zebadiah;</hi> they ſhould meet in one to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult vpon <hi>negotia Iehouae, Regit, &amp; Reipub.</hi> the buſineſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:20215:19"/>God, the King, and Common-wealth: like both our hands, they ſhould worke together, for the whole body of the kingdome; ſo that both be ſubiect vnto the king, which in this is not <hi>mere laicus,</hi> a meere Lay-man, much leſſe a Clerke; but like the ſoule, which does all in all, yet is not any part; like a center, in whom the lines of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior powers do meete, yet is no line; like the Sun, which works contraries by the ſame force, yet feeles not the mixture of any ſuch qualities.</p>
            <p>Thus the Kings of Iſrael had <hi>poteſtatem directiuam,</hi> and <hi>correctiuam</hi> ouer Prieſts and people; <hi>Dauid</hi> as hee ruled theſe prudently with all his power, hee ſet them likewiſe in their orders: <hi>Salomon</hi> as he iudged betwixt harlots, he depoſed <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and put <hi>Zadocke</hi> in his roome: <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> as hee ſent the Iudges, hee ſent the Prieſts and Leuites into the prouinces. Let euery ſoule then ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the ſoule of the Prieſt, ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> as well as of the people, euen the ſoule of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (which was one of the Romane Church) be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto theſe higher powers. To determine all in a word, we may conclude; the Pope (as <hi>Blackwell</hi> ſaith) hath ability to rule Princes when they be willing, but the king hath authority to rule men, whether they will or no: the Pope may be Chriſts Vicar like other Prieſts, when he preaches and miniſters the Sacraments in ſteed of him; but the king is Gods Vicegerent (as <hi>Anaſtaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Pope, called <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius</hi> the Pope entituled <hi>Lucius</hi> king of Britaine) to iudge and execute his iudgements vpon earth: the Pope may barre the king from his Maſſes, indulgences, and his owne oriſons; and the king may barre the Pope from intermedling with his kingdomes. Let them like <hi>Iacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Laban</hi> not paſſe this pillar towards one another,
<pb facs="tcp:20215:20"/>for euill: and all things elſe will quietly be compoſed.</p>
            <p>But if by violence of his excommunications the Pope licence any to take armes, he goes beyond his teddar, and knowes not of what ſpirit he is: for as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith of <hi>Eugenius, in criminibus, non poſſeſſionibus poteſtas veſtra, praeuaricatores excluſura, non poſseſsores:</hi> Your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer conſiſteth not in expelling any from poſſeſſion, but in expelling ſin from them; the keyes of heauen were not giuen vnto ſuch purpoſes; the rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> may bee turned into a Serpent, but the rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> buddeth &amp; bodeth peace. <hi>Dauid</hi> could not build the Temple being ſtained with bloud. <hi>Paul</hi> proteſted, he was pure from the bloud of all. <hi>Gregory</hi> though he might haue kild the Gothes, he woud not meddle in ſuch bloudy matters; &amp; ſhall the pillars of the Sanctuary, the ſucceſſors of S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> fil their heartes and hands with ſuch practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes? Euer bleſſed bee the Right worthy Earle of <hi>Sariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury: Qui baculum fixit:</hi> which hath ſet his reſt on this, that neuer any Proteſtant regular, or vnconformitant, did euer mingle their differences with bloudy maſſacres? but it was excellently noted of the moſt noble &amp; learned Earle of <hi>Northampton:</hi> that there was neuer any diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the ſtate without a Prieſt. By their fruites then you ſhall know them: Enuie, ſtrife, and ſedition is from a wiſedome which is earthly, ſenſuall and diuelliſh; but the wiſedome from aboue is pure, and peaceable, eaſie to be entreated; &amp; the fruites of righteouſneſſe are ſowne in peace, of them which make peace.</p>
            <p>Excommunication is not now worſe then in the daies of <hi>Samuel,</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> had bene accurſt of God, ſo farre, that he might not be praied, or mourned for; yet he could not be killed or depriued of <hi>Dauid</hi> the next an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed: not worſe, then in the daies of Chriſt, which
<pb facs="tcp:20215:20"/>would haue vs count excommunicates for heathens &amp; publicans; yet himſelfe would eate, and ciuilly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with them: not worſe, then in the daies of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who deliuered ouer an inceſtuous perſon vnto ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, that his ſpirit might be ſaued in the day of the Lord. Now their ſpirit cannot be ſaued, if they be ſlaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate. The company that he forbids, is not that we ſhould vtterly forſake their ſociety, for then we muſt forſake the world; but that we ſhould abſtaine from their communion; wee ſhould not eate with them of the ſame vnleauened paſſeouer Chriſt Ieſus; wee ſhould ſeeke to reſtore them in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe: wee ſhould ſtriue to doe good vnto all, though they be not of the houſhold of faith. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> thought it ſufficient, that the excommunicate was rebuked of many; but our Aduerſaries are not ſatisfied vnleſſe they take life and al. God baniſht <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradice, and yet he gaue him certaine meanes to liue. Gods holy Spirit parted from the former world, yet he left them one hundred and twenty yeares leaſure to repent themſelues. God ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered <hi>Mirian</hi> from the campe, yet hee would haue the people to ſtay for her, that ſhe ſhould not vtterly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate: and ſhall wee cenſure more ſeuerely then the Lord of hoaſts? Hereupon their owne decrees affirme, that excommunication is not <hi>mortalis,</hi> but <hi>medicinalis gladius;</hi> not a killing but healing ſword. Saint <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith, it is not <hi>Corporalis,</hi> but <hi>Spiritualis poena;</hi> a penaltie for the ſoule, not for the body. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſhews the very caſe: ſuppoſe an euill doer cannot be ſeuered without ſedition: <hi>Tolera Zizanium, eſlo frumentum.</hi> be wheat, and beare with tares. Thus did Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate <hi>Theodoſius:</hi> his threatning was, <hi>Rogamus, non pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> wee cannot fight, but pray: <hi>Lachrimae ſunt arma:</hi> tis
<pb facs="tcp:20215:21"/>the teares of our eyes, not weapons in our hands, which muſt ouercome you; our warfare is not carnall but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and mighty through God: wee muſt fight with knowledge againſt ignorance, with humility againſt pride, with examples of obedience, againſt wilfulneſſe in wickedneſſe. How many Iewes, Turks, Atheiſts, Epicures and murderers doth God now ſuffer in this world, and ſets a marke on them as on <hi>Cain,</hi> that none ſhall kill, vntill he pleaſe to take them hence? can any thing then be ſo ſhameles vnder the pretence of religion to murder whom they liſt, as that Frier did, who ſlew ſixe ſcore with his owne hands in a French maſſacre? Their doctrine therefore cannot be but impious againſt God in depoſing or abuſing his officers, for he will take it, as if it were himſelfe, as he ſaid of <hi>Samuel,</hi> they haue not caſt away thee, but me. It is hereticall againſt the Scripture, which commands the contrary, truth, loue, and peace; it is abhominable, and ſo damnable in their owne conſcience, the cenſure of the world, and the ſight of God: Although the Popes propoſe it as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorius, yet their guilty conſcience foretelleth heauy things, and in their hearts <hi>proditionem amant, nov prodito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem:</hi> they loue the deed as far as it profits them, but the doer they will haue in bitter deteſtation; much more the world hateth this, and for it owne ſafety, will not ſuffer ſuch a ſinne vnpuniſht. Nature abhors mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as appeares by the bleeding of the murdered in the preſence of the murderer: much more the murders of a Prince, whoſe life hath bene accounted ſacred in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, countries and religions; much more vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of religion, when Gods Holineſſe is made a patron of ſuch diuelliſh treacheries: and therfore in his iudgment hee will puniſh the leſſe offenders with leſſe torments,
<pb facs="tcp:20215:21"/>and theſe with worſt and moſt, as being moſt miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous men. Thus their opinion muſt needes be abſurd, which puls all kings &amp; kingdoms from Gods power, &amp; leaues them in the diſpoſition of a weake old ſinful man. As then this oath may betaken with a good conſcience: being vndertaken it muſt be kept notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding al ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, it may be wiſdome, as times alter to change an opinion, but it is impietie to breake a reſolution groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on Gods word. <hi>Zachariah</hi> beheld a flying booke, the length was 20, the bredth was 10 cubits, which entred into the ſwearers houſe, and eate vp the timber &amp; ſtones thereof; but now we may behold a flying bul of mighty voyce, but little force, which coms from <hi>Rome</hi> to licence &amp; command many to forſweare themſelues, <hi>Violare De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum non licet acta Deum;</hi> if one Magiſtrat infringe what an other hath determined, there followes nothing but confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. God although that he promiſt, whatſoeuer we bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or looſed on earth, ſhold be ſo bound or looſed in heauen, yet he neuer promiſt, we might looſe on earth, what was already bound in heauen. Woe to them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which call euil good, &amp; good euill, which <hi>de iuſtitia</hi> would make <hi>iniuſtitiam,</hi> and breake the ſeauen-fold bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of an oath, as the Hebrew name imports; as <hi>Samſon</hi> did the new made cords, with little force or care: who can this be but Anti-chriſt? who ſitting in the Temple of God, would exalt himſelfe aboue God ſo far, as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the bonds made ſacred by his holyname? and bring that blemiſh vpon Chriſtianity, which euen Iewes and Turks abhorre; who ſay the cauſes of our Chriſtian trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are our daily blaſphemies &amp; periuries. This doctrine of abſolution is ſo contrary to inward peace &amp; outward honeſty, ſo odious in it ſelfe, perilous for example, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous to the Church, preiudicious in the confederacies
<pb facs="tcp:20215:22"/>of Princes, and ſuſpicious in all contracts; for if our couenants be neuer ſo ſurely writ on earth, and regiſtred in heauen; yet they ſay, they may be cancelled of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, that it cannot be ſuffered in a Chriſtian common wealth; looke then into the word of God, whether it be better obeying the king in keeping of a lawfull oath, then a ſtranger in breaking it; looke into thy conſcience whether it can be diſcharged of periury by the bull of ſuch a Biſhop: looke vnto the iudgement of all fleſh, whether the Popes pardons, can proue a <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hell. Thus we muſt not looke for abſolution. Equiuocation and mentall reſeruation is as dangerous, they be ſolaeciſmes in reaſon, much more abſurd in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience &amp; Chriſtianity. This was <hi>Lyſanders</hi> noted crime to deceiue children with triffles, and men with oathes. This was that heinous fault of <hi>Ananias<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> hee told not all he ſhould haue told: but kept halfe backe for his owne profit, and ſo lied againſt the holy Ghoſt This was the cuſtome of hereticks, to proteſt one faith, and haue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their boſome. This is the ſhame of Chriſtendom: ſince this doctrine was defended, men make a common trade of lying and deceiuing. This is the heart, and the heart, whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo complaines; the diſſembling to ſatisfie for the preſent, which <hi>Eleazar</hi> much abhorred: the trick of a falſe brother, which had the voyce of <hi>Iacob</hi> and the hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> he ſpoke like a friend, and dealt like an enimie. The Satyre could not abide him could blow both hot and could. <hi>Solon</hi> condemned <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ambidexters in their words and deedes. God will not ſuffer men to halt betweene two opinions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtians ſhould hate ſuch amphibologies, as they loue God, reaſon, and religion.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the ſcope and duties of this oath are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,
<pb facs="tcp:20215:22"/>being faith, loue and peace. The example hath ben ſorted in many Councels, Fathers &amp; hiſtories: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is a conſcionable proteſtation of a loyall heart. This oath is like <hi>ſhibboleth:</hi> if you pronounce it right, you ſhal bee receiued: if not, reiected: like <hi>Ioſhuaes</hi> queſtion, art thou on ourſide, or on our aduerſaries? like <hi>Ichues</hi> demand of <hi>Ionadab:</hi> if thine heart bee right towards me, as mine towards thee, then aſcend into my chariot: if you loue the ſafegard of your Prince, as hee tenders your ſafety, you ſhall purchaſe his fauour: take it then as giuen by good authority. Prayer is a duty moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to be made for Kings; we muſt not pray without faith, for without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God: what wee beleeue we may well ſweare, and therefore we may ſweare for our Princes honour and ſafety: an oath is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an end of all controuerſie. Now there is a controuerſie, whether he which takes the Pope for his God, can take the King for his maiſter; and this oath wil determine it. An oath is to be taken ſaith <hi>Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> either to cleere thy ſelfe of ſome filthy crime; and what fowler then high treaſon? or to free thy friend from a danger: and what greater then ſuch a ſuſpicion? It is reaſon they that receiue protection, ſhould promiſe loue and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to him which is the cauſe of: it is honeſt to profeſſe with our mouthes, what wee meane in our heartes, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance where it is deſerued. It is a duty which the Pope in far ſtricter terms exacts of al Emperours, Ieſuits, Prieſts and Auertites, from our profeſſion why: ſhould not Chriſtian kings require all faithfulneſſe of their ſubiects? Kings may command a publicke faſt; as the King of <hi>Niniue</hi> did vnto man and beaſt: or publike feaſtes as <hi>Mardochaeus</hi> and <hi>Maccabaeus</hi> did vnto the <hi>Iewes:</hi> or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb facs="tcp:20215:23"/>oblations, as <hi>Moſes</hi> to the making of the Tabernacle; and <hi>Ioſiah</hi> to the repairing of the Temple; or publicke prayers, as <hi>Dauid</hi> indited holy Pſalmes to be ſung in the Sanctuary, and therefore may compoſe, and impoſe an oath, which is not ſo praeciſe a part of religion: an oath is vſed in couenants of reconcilement, as betweene <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Abimelech;</hi> and ſhould not we rather be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled with our King then a ſtranger? it is a motiue of diligence, as when <hi>Saul</hi> ſwore the Souldiers they ſhould not eate, they were more earneſt vpon their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies: it is as a vow before God and man, of that which law, conſcience, and humanity requireth at our hands: and vowes in lawfull matters are neuer to be reproued. This was vſed of heathens amongſt themſelues, as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> cittizens were ſworne vnto their lawes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; of Chriſtians to heathens, as the Chriſtian Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers did <hi>praeſtare Sacramentum;</hi> take a ſacred oath of their Captaines to reſt at their command; of heathens to the faithfull, as <hi>Iacob</hi> tooke an oath of <hi>Laban</hi> ſwearing by his Gods: <hi>Iuſiur andum</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>quia ius omne, nihil niſi ius iurandum eſt;</hi> wee ſhould ſo much obſerue the lawes that we might ſweare the performance; Kings being keepers of each table, may ſweare their ſubiects to the keeping of both lawes; moſt chiefly that which concernes God or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: for they be firſt &amp; chiefly meant &amp; mentioned in the commandments: let me then ſay with <hi>Salomon,</hi> I aduertiſe thee to take heed vnto the mouth of the king, and the wordes of the oath of God: for the Kings ſake obſerue the oath, for the oaths ſake obſerue the King, for Gods ſake obſerue both God, oath, and King.</p>
            <p>Oh bleſſed God by whom Kings reigne, and Princes decree iuſtice, preſerue thy Seruant our Soueraigne in thy truth, peace and loue: ſet him as a ſignet on thine
<pb facs="tcp:20215:23"/>hart: with inward grace and fauour ſtill embrace and encreaſe him: ſet him as a ſignet on thy hand, with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force and power ſtill protect and defend him: giue him a long life, a ſafe eſtate, a wiſe heart, a louing care, honour amongſt his owne, and victories againſt his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Grant this moſt mercifull Father for thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus ſake, to whom with thee &amp; thy moſt holy Spirit, be giuen honour and dominion now and euer: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
